at people's homes and business rooftops. We looked at pesticide levels. We thought there would be less pesticides in areas where bees are doing better. That's not the case. So what we found here in our study is -- the orange bars are Boston, and we thought those bars would be the lowest, there would be the lowest levels of pesticides. And, in fact, there are the most pesticides in cities. So the pesticide hypothesis for what's saving bees -- less pesticides in cities -- is not it. And this is very typical of my life as a scientist. Anytime I've had a hypothesis, not only is it not supported, but the opposite is true. (Laughter) Which is still an interesting finding, right? We moved on. The disease hypothesis. We looked at diseases all over our beehives. And what we found in a similar study to this one with North Carolina State is: there's no difference between disease in bees in urban, suburban and rural areas. Diseases are everywhere; bees are sick and dying. In fact, there were more diseases of bees in cities. This was from Raleigh, North Carolina. So again, my hypothesis was not supported. The opposite was true. We're moving on. (Laughter) The habitat hypothesis. This said that areas where bees are thriving have a better habitat -- more flowers, right? But we didn't know how to test this. So I had a really interesting meeting. An idea sparked with my friend and colleague Anne Madden, fellow TED speaker. We thought about genomics, kind of like AncestryDNA or 23andMe. Have you done these? You spit in a tube and you find out, "I'm German!" (Laughter) Well, we developed this for honey. So we have a sample of honey and we look at all the plant DNA, and we find out, "I'm sumac!" (Laughter) And that's what we found here in Provincetown. So for the first time ever, I'm able to report to you what type of honey is from right here in our own community. HoneyDNA, a genomics test. Spring honey in Provincetown is from privet. What's privet? Hedges. What's the message? Don't trim your hedges to save the bees. (Laughter) I know we're getting crunchy and it's controversial, so before you throw your tomatoes, we'll move to the summer honey, which is water lily honey. If you have honey from Provincetown right here in the summer, you're eating water lily juice; in the fall, sumac honey. We're learning about our food for the first time ever. And now we're able to report, if you need to do any city planning: What are good things to plant? What do we know the bees are going to that's good for your garden? For the first time ever for any community, we now know this answer. What's more interesting for us is deeper in the data. So, if you're from the Caribbean and you want to explore your heritage, Bahamian honey is from the laurel family, cinnamon and avocado flavors. But what's more interesting is 85 different plant species in one teaspoon of honey. That's the measure we want, the big data. Indian honey: that is oak. Every sample we've tested from India is oak, and that's 172 different flavors in one taste of Indian honey. Provincetown honey goes from 116 plants in the spring to over 200 plants in the summer. These are the numbers that we need to test the habitat hypothesis. In another citizen science approach, you find out about your food and we get some interesting data. We're finding out now that in rural areas, there are 150 plants on average in a sample of honey. That's a measure for rural. Suburban areas, what might you think? Do they have less or more plants in suburban areas with lawns that look nice for people but they're terrible for pollinators? Suburbs have very low plant diversity, so if you have a beautiful lawn, good for you, but you can do more. You can have a patch of your lawn that's a wildflower meadow to diversify your habitat, to improve pollinator health. Anybody can do this. Urban areas have the most habitat, best habitat, as you can see here: over 200 different plants. We have, for the first time ever, support for the habitat hypothesis. We also now know how we can work with cities. The City of Boston has eight times better habitat than its nearby suburbs. And so when we work with governments, we can scale this. You might think on my tombstone, it'll say, "Here lies Noah. Plant a flower." Right? I mean -- it's exhausting after all of this. But when we scale together, when we go to governments and city planners -- like in Boston, the honey is mostly linden trees, and we say, "If a dead tree needs to be replaced, consider linden." When we take this information to governments, we can do amazing things. This is a rooftop from Fred's company. We can plant those things on top of rooftops worldwide to start restoring habitat and securing food systems. We've worked with the World Bank and the presidential delegation from the country of Haiti. We've worked with wonderful graduate students at Yale University and Ethiopia. In these countries, we can add value to their honey by identifying what it is, but informing the people of what to plant to restore their habitat and secure their food systems. But what I think is even more important is when we think about natural disasters. For the first time, we now know how we can have a baseline measure of any habitat before it might be destroyed. Think about your hometown. What risks does the environment pose to it? This is how we're going to save Puerto Rico after Hurricane Maria. We now have a baseline measure of honey, honey DNA from before and after the storm. We started in Humacao. This is right where Hurricane Maria made landfall. And we know what plants to replace and in what quantity and where by triangulating honey DNA samples. You might even think about right here, the beautiful land that connected us, that primed us, all the citizen science to begin with, the erosion, the winter storms that are getting more violent every year. What are we going to do about this, our precious land? Well, looking at honey DNA, we can see what plants are good for pollinators that have deep roots, that can secure the land, and together, everybody can participate. And the solution fits in a teaspoon. If your hometown might get swept away or destroyed by a natural disaster, we now have a blueprint suspended in time for how to restore that on Earth, or perhaps even in a greenhouse on Mars. I know it sounds crazy, but think about this: a new Provincetown, a new hometown, a place that might be familiar that's also good for pollinators for a stable food system, when we're thinking about the future. Now, together, we know what's saving bees -- by planting diverse habitat. Now, together, we know how bees are going to save us -- by being barometers for environmental health, by being blueprints, sources of information, little data factories suspended in time. Thank you. (Applause)
sur les maisons ou les immeubles. On a étudié les résultats. On pensait trouver moins de pesticides là où les abeilles se portent mieux. Ce n'était pas le cas. On a trouvé dans notre étude, les barres orange c'est Boston, on a pensé que ces barres seraient plus basses, avec le niveau de pesticides le plus bas. En fait, on a plus de pesticides dans les villes. Donc l’hypothèse du pesticide qui sauve les abeilles... moins de pesticides en ville n'est pas correcte. Et c'est typique dans ma vie de scientifique. A chaque fois que je fais une hypothèse, c'est son contraire qui se vérifie. (Rires) C'est une trouvaille intéressante hein ? Passons à autre chose. L’hypothèse des maladies On a examiné les maladies de toutes nos ruches. On a trouvé dans une étude similaire en Caroline du Nord : aucune différence entre les maladies en zone urbaine, suburbaine, rurale. Partout les abeilles sont malades et mourantes, il y a plus de maladies des abeilles dans les villes. Comme ici à Raleigh, en Caroline du Nord. Une fois de plus, le contraire de mon hypothèse de départ se vérifie. Continuons. (Rires) L’hypothèse de l’habitat. Les zones où les abeilles sont prospères auraient un meilleur habitat -- plus de fleurs, ok ? On ne savait pas comment tester ça. J’ai donc eu une réunion très intéressante. Une idée a germé avec mon amie et collègue Anne Madden, intervenante TED. On a pensé à la génomique, comme AncestryDNA ou 23andMe. Avez-vous fait ces tests ? Vous crachez dans un tube et dites « Je suis allemand ! » (Rires) On a développé ça pour le miel. Avec un échantillon de miel on regarde tout l’ADN de la plante, et on dit « je suis sumac ! » (Rires) Et c’est ce qu’on a trouvé ici à Provincetown. Donc pour la toute première fois, je vous rapporte quel type de miel vient d’ici de notre propre communauté. HoneyDNA, un test de génomique. Le miel de printemps à Provincetown vient du troène. C'est quoi le troène ? Des haies. Quel est le message ? Ne coupez pas vos haies pour sauver les abeilles. (Rires) Je sais que ça fait baba cool et c’est controversé, avant de nous lancer des tomates, allons vers du miel d’été, qui est du miel de nénuphar. Si vous avez du miel de Provincetown, ici en été, vous mangerez du jus de nénuphar, et à l'automne, du miel de sumac. On apprend sur la nourriture comme jamais auparavant. Et on peut désormais donner pour n'importe quel aménagement urbain les bonnes plantes à cultiver, et ce que les abeilles feront pour le bien de votre jardin. Pour la 1ere fois pour chaque communauté on a la réponse. Le plus intéressant pour nous est en approfondissant les données. Si vous venez des Caraïbes et voulez explorer votre patrimoine, Le miel bahaméen provient de la famille du laurier, avec des saveurs cannelle et avocat. C'est incroyable de trouver 85 espèces de plantes dans une seule cuillère de miel. C’est la mesure que nous voulons, les mégadonnées. Le miel indien : c'est du chêne. Chaque échantillon de ce type vient du chêne, 172 variétés de saveurs dans dans un bout de miel indien. Le miel de Provincetown part de 116 plantes au printemps jusqu'à 200 plantes en été. C'est le nombre pour tester l'hypothèse de l'habitat. Dans une autre approche, sur la nourriture nous obtenons des bonnes données. Nous découvrons que dans les régions rurales un échantillon de miel contient en moyenne 150 plantes. C'est une mesure à la campagne. Les banlieusards, vous en pensez quoi ? Plus ou moins de plantes dans les banlieues avec pelouses, jolies pour nous mais terrible pour les pollinisateurs? Les banlieues ont une très faible diversité végétale, donc si vous avez une belle pelouse, tant mieux pour vous, mais vous pouvez faire plus. En plantant des fleurs sauvages sur une partie de votre pelouse pour diversifier l'habitat, pour améliorer la santé des pollinisateurs. Tout le monde peut faire ça. Les zones urbaines ont le meilleur biotope vous voyez ici : plus de 200 plantes différentes. Pour la 1ere fois, l'hypothèse sur l'habitat se vérifie. Nous savons aussi comment travailler avec les villes. La ville de Boston a un biotope huit fois meilleur que ses banlieues proches. On peut l'étendre à l'échelle gouvernementale. Vous penserez ma pierre tombale dira : « Ici git Noé, plantez une fleur. » N'est ce pas ? Je veux dire...c’est épuisant après tout ça. Quand on regarde l'ensemble, les gouvernements, les urbanistes... à Boston, le miel vient des arbres de tilleul, on leur dit : « si un arbre meurt remplacez-le, pensez au tilleul. » On peut faire des grandes choses en travaillant avec les autorités. Là c'est le toit de l'entreprise Fred. On peut planter ces trucs sur les toits du monde entier pour restaurer l’habitat et sécuriser l'alimentation. On a travaillé avec la Banque Mondiale et la délégation présidentielle de Haiti. On a travaillé avec des diplômés de Yale et d'Ethiopie. Dans ces pays, nous ajoutons de la valeur au miel en l'identifiant, en les aidant sur quoi planter pour restaurer leur biotope et sécuriser l'alimentation. Mais quand on pense aux catastrophes naturelles. Pour la première fois, nous pouvons obtenir une mesure complète de tout biotope avant qu'il soit détruit. Pensez à votre ville natale. Quels sont les risques causés par l’environnement ? Comment nous allons sauver Porto Rico après l’ouragan Maria Nous avons maintenant une mesure de base du miel, l'ADN du miel avant et après la tempête. Nous avons commencé à Humacao. C’est là que l’ouragan Maria a frappé. Nous savons quelles plantes remplacer, la quantité et où, en triangulant des échantillons d’ADN de miel. On peut même penser que ici, la belle terre qui nous connecte, qui nous a façonnés, toute la science citoyenne, l’érosion, les tempêtes d’hiver qui deviennent plus violentes chaque année. Qu’allons-nous faire à ce sujet pour notre terre précieuse ? En regardant l’ADN du miel, on voit les plantes bonnes pour les pollinisateurs à racine profonde qui sécurisent la terre, et ensemble, tout le monde peut participer et la solution tient dans une cuillère à café. Si votre ville natale est balayée par une catastrophe naturelle, nous avons maintenant un plan prêt à l'emploi pour tout réparer sur Terre, ou peut-être même dans une serre sur Mars. Je sais que ça semble fou, mais pensez à ceci : un nouveau Provincetown, une nouvelle ville natale, un endroit familier qui serait aussi bon pour les pollinisateurs pour une alimentation stable dans le futur. Maintenant, ensemble, nous savons ce qui sauve les abeilles... en plantant des biotopes variés. Ensemble, nous savons comment les abeilles vont nous sauver -- en étant des baromètres de la santé environnementale, en étant des plans, des sources d’information, petites usines de données suspendues dans le temps. Merci. (Applaudissements)